Guide to the Sidney Kaufman Papers, circa 1930-2007.
Kaufman, Sidney Papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Sidney Kaufman Papers, circa 1930-2007.
16-14-4201
Kaufman, Sidney
2.5
Correspondence, maps/charts, movie film, newspapers, photographs, publications, reports, research material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers include material on earthquakes and seismology, elastic waves, nuclear and underwater explosions, his work during employment with Shell Oil Company and material while a professor at Cornell, including course notes and COCORP items. Also, his work with the Navy Navigation Satellite System, radiolocation, and Shell's analog computer. In addition, photographs/negatives and ephemera from his student years at Cornell and a set of Gemini photographs from NASA.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Sidney Kaufman obtained his BS degree from Cornell in 1930 and his Ph.D. degree in Physics from Cornell in 1934. He worked for Shell Oil Company, during which he is credited with the world's first offshore seismic survey for oil, carried out in the 1940's. Sid left his senior position at Shell to join Cornell as Acting Professor in 1973 (Dept. of Geological Sciences, now titled Earth and Atmospheric Sciences). Along with Emeritus Professor Jack Oliver, Sid initiated the Consortium for Continental Reflection Profiling (COCORP) project at Cornell, which pioneered in the use of oil exploration techniques to study the deep structure of the continents. In 1983 Sid received the Virgil Kauffman Gold Medal Award from the Society of Exploration Geophysicists for outstanding contribution to the advancement of the science of geophysical exploration.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers include material on earthquakes and seismology, elastic waves, nuclear and underwater explosions, his work during employment with Shell Oil Company and material while a professor at Cornell, including course notes and COCORP items. Also, his work with the Navy Navigation Satellite System, radiolocation, and Shell's analog computer. In addition, photographs/negatives and ephemera from his student years at Cornell and a set of Gemini photographs from NASA.
Also, a VHS tape titled "Recollections by Sidney Kaufman". In 2003, a group of people met with Sidney Kaufman for an interview. He discussed many aspects of his life, including being a student and teaching at Cornell, his wife and jobs, WWII, and radar.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Kaufman, Sidney 1908-2008.; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.); Shell Oil Company.; Society of Exploration Geophysicists.; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration
Subjects:
Geophysics.; Geophysical field investigations; Seismology.; Earthquakes.; Satellites.; Petroleum -- Prospecting; Analog computers.; Nuclear explosions.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Course notes for GS487, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Course material for GS488, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Papers/articles about Sidney Kaufman, 1983-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Kaufman reprints, 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to Kaufman, 1965-2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  -especially regarding appointments to various committees and positions
- Keichi Kasahara material, 1952-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- NAS annual meeting, abstracts of papers, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- NRL work, ca. 1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Society of Exploration Geophysicists (SEG), 1973-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- SEG 50th anniversary, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- SEG awards program, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Shell contract material, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Shell's analog computer, ca. 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Analog computer photos, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Shell 50th anniversary, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Koninklijke/Shell Exploratie en Produktie Laboratorium, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Meeting of Charles Coffin and Gerard Swope Fellows, General Electric, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- University of California - Institute of Geophysics and Planetary Physics, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Cornell Program for the Study of the Continents, 1982-1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Consortium for Continental Reflection Profiling (COCORP), 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- COCORP charts, graphs and maps, ca. 1970's - 1980's (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Field photos (COCORP?), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Oil seep photos, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Oil-Industry History, volume 5, 6 and 8, 2004-2007 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Weizmann Institute of Science trip, Rehovoth, Israel, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- China trip, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  -contains additional COCORP material
- Preliminary reports, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  -Lake Verret
  -Valentine
  -Six Mile Lake
  -Duson, Cankton, Egan
  -St. Francisville
- Various Notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Navy Navigation Satellite system, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Navy Navigation Satellite system, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Radiolocation systems, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Geophysics material, ca. 1970's-1980's (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Elastic waves, effects on fish life, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Nuclear weapons and explosions, 1960, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Earthquakes and seismology, 1963-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Earthquakes and seismology, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Lawrence Livermore Lab - consultation documents, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- An analysis of the potential use of geothermal energy for power generation along the Texas Gulf coast, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- External review of the graduate program in geophysics at St. Louis University, by Kaufman, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- The propagation of energy according to the classical theory, by Kaufman, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- The Cornell Physics Department, Recollections and a History of Sorts, by Paul Hartman, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  -Kaufman mentioned on page 69
- Information Theory text by W. W. Ogden, ca. 1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Cornell Engineering, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Cornell alumni news and mailing list, 1980, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Cornell alumni material, 1997-2000) (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Cornell Widow, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Photos and ephemera - Cornell, ca. 1930's (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Sidney Kaufman portraits, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Various group photos, ca. 1950's-1960's (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Family, friends, reunion photos, ca. 1960's-2000's (Box 2, Folder 19)
- NASA - Gemini photos, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  -includes photos of various geological locations on Earth
- Unidentified photos, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Recollections by Sidney Kaufman, VHS tape, 2003; V-7600 (Box 2)
- Various note books, n.d. (Box 2)
- Reprints collected by Kaufman while at Cornell, n.d. (Box 2)
- Various plaques and certificates, 1938-1964 (Box 3)
- Petroleum Prospecting conference in China - group photo of attendees, 1981 (Map-case Folder 1)
- "One In Sixteen" Shell Oil poster featuring Kaufman, n.d. (Map-case Folder 1)